Bruno P. Kinoshita

(021) 104 2131 • ☑ kinow@apache.org • ☑ kinoshita.eti.br
 in brunopkinoshita • ☑ kinow • ☑ kinow
 Brazilian, married, 36 years old, non-smoker

I am an honest, and focused Software Engineer that is always trying to deliver solutions with quality. I am very calm and easy-going, and enjoy a challenging work environment, Open Source, and learning about different cultures.

I have worked in many different projects for the past ten years, in industries such as telecommunications, banking, credit, retail, insurance, and start-ups. Occupied different positions including programmer, quality engineer, devops, architect, full stack developer, and big data engineer.

I am fluent in English and Portuguese, with good understanding of Spanish, and basic of Japanese. Attended Te Reo Maori beginner classes to learn basic vocabulary and pronunciation. ORCID ID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8250-4074

Skills

Languages	Java, Python, PHP, R, C/C++, CSS, HTML, JavaScript, Shell, Perl, SQL
Frameworks	Node.js, NumPy, Pandas, Spark, Spring, SpringBoot, Struts, Hadoop, Tornado,
	Laravel
GIS	PostGIS, QGIS, ArcGIS, gvSIG, WFS, WMS, SOS, and other OGC standards
Systems	Linux, OSX, Windows

Achievements

o GSoC Mentor, Jenkins Machine Learning Plug-in	March 2020, to September 2020
o Invited to become an Apache Software Foundation Member	March 2018
o Invited to become an Apache OpenNLP PMC	July 2017
o Invited to become an Apache OpenNLP Committer	April 2017
o Invited to become an Apache Commons PMC	October 2016
o Invited to become an Apache Jena PMC	March 2015
o Invited to become an Apache Jena Committer	January 2015
o Invited to become an Apache Commons Committer	August 2012
o Organized two Jenkins meetups in Sao Paulo, Brazil	2012 and 2013

Awards

o Spirit of GovHack for amazing team work. Auckland, New Zealand.	July 2016
o NIWA Proactive Communicator. Auckland, New Zealand.	February 2016

Education

o Diploma in Business Administration, Mackenzie University	January 2008 – July 2009
o B.S. in Information Systems, Mackenzie University	August 2003 – July 2007
o Colegio Centenario (Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo, Brazil)	December 2002

Work Experience

o Research Software Engineer, N/WA

October 2018 – Today

- Working remotely from Auckland on Cylc, an Open Source python cycling meta-scheduler, used to run forecast model as well as other types of jobs
- Adding code coverage reports, and increasing the test coverage preparing for upcoming changes
- Porting Python code from Python 2 to Python 3
- Development of Vue.JS user interfaces
- GraphQL, Tornado, Flask, and web development
- Graph algorithms

o Java Engineer, NIWA

Jun 2017 - Sep 2018

- Java development in the IT Systems Development team. Working on **EcoConnect**, NIWA's specialist environmental forecasting and information service.
- Refactoring of old Java stack, migrating JEE applications from GlassFish, JBoss, and WebLogic to a common architecture.

o Full Stack Software Developer, Spark Ventures

Oct 2016 - Jun 2017

- Java development in the Platform team, crafting solutions common to all other teams.
- Integration between AWS KMS and Spring Boot applications.
- **New Relic** configuration to set up alerts and monitoring for all internal applications, and also for external services such as **Zuora**, **Stormpath**, and **Prismic**.
- Bamboo restructuration, adding groups, cleaning up users, automating a few tasks, and generating user and operational documentation.
- Review security of build system, Spring boot applications, and AWS resources.

o Software Developer / Operations, NIWA

Apr 2015 - Sep 2016

- Responsible for the **Continuous Integration** and development pipeline in **Jenkins**.
- Introduced **monitoring** of the development lifecycle activities with dashboards written in Node.js and using the **Dashing** framework.
- Responsible for maintaining the middleware stack, including **GeoServer**, **GeoNetworks**, **IPT**, **PostGIS**, **SOS** servers, vocabulary servers, and other internal systems.
- Worked closely with researchers writing Python tools and utilities for weather, remote-sensing, tracking, data processing, and general automation.
- Review internal infrastructure looking for security problems.
- Created company first public **git** repositories under a new organization in GitHub.

o **Senior Big Data Engineer**, *Boa Vista Servicos (Equifax)*

Jun 2014 – Mar 2015

- Deployed a 8-node **Hadoop** cluster, with **Hive**, **Impala**, and **HDFS**.
- Created ontologies to match the data in the cluster with the data modeled by the data architecture department.
- Wrote web applications in Java with **Jersey** and **JOOQ**, and in PHP with **Laravel** to interface with the data generated after it was combined with the ontologies.
- Data ingestion automation with **crawlers** written in Python, parsing PDF files in Java with statistical tool.
- Meetings with internal departments to discuss project needs, and with external vendors to assess solutions, and RFP's and RFQ's
- Integrate Talend with **Tableau**, and IBM Nettezza
- Created monitoring dashboards for data arriving in the cluster
- Wrote initial jobs for parsing data collected by crawlers, combining with logs and other internal data dumps. Creating a benchmark, and comparison reports for the upper management.

o Senior Software Architect, Tokio Marine

Jan 2013 - May 2014

- Set up an **ActiveMQ** cluster with queues persisted in **Oracle**, and used by different internal departments.
- Participation in assessments for new solutions, and meetings with vendors.

- Organized internal workshops and trainings for the development teams.
- Created RESTful internal services for sending SMS, and signing PDF files.
- Set up the company SSO solution with **OpenAM**.
- Helped to set up authentication in **Liferay** with the new SSO solution.
- Created company-wide monitoring solution for both technical metrics and business KPI's.

o Senior Infrastructure Engineer, Tokio Marine

Oct 2012 - Dec 2013

- Automate infrastructure with **Shell**, **Jenkins**, and **Puppet**.
- Replace legacy OC4J servers by a new **JBoss** cluster.
- Update linux boxes to use services to start systems at startup, have a uniform logging settings, review log rotation settings, and integrated user authentication and sudoers.
- Automated parts of the software deployment that was a complete manual process before.

o Senior Software Engineer, Tokio Marine

Oct 2011 - Sep 2012

- Helped to maintain legacy systems written for an internal portal solution.
- Mavenized systems written with Ant, Shell, and Ivy.
- Created **Subversion** hooks to trigger jobs in Jenkins.
- Created daily builds in Jenkins for the company portal.

o Senior System Analyst, Lojas Riachuelo

Jul 2011 - Sep 2011

- Refactor old Java Swing application to improve threading and **OO design**.
- Suggest a different architecture for the company POS system written in Java.
- Split POS legacy system in Maven modules.
- Wrote first automated tests for the POS system.
- Create wrappers for the **Delphi** and **C/C++** devices used by the POS (e.g. printer, biometric devices).

o Senior Software Quality Engineer, Vivo (Telefonica)

Jan 2010 - Jun 2011

- Gathering metrics from company CRM and modules, and analyse bugs and improvements
- Set up complete QA environment in **CentOS**, with tools such as **Hudson**, **Sonar**, **TestLink**, **FishEye**, and **JIRA**.
- Wrote an Open Source plugin for Jenkins to provide integration for TestLink
- Debug and profile the company CRM with **YourKit**, and **Eclipse Memory Analyzer**.
- Wrote performance tests with JMeter and SOAP-UI.
- Wrote company-wide tools to help different departments automating tasks.
- Participate in the company and partners RFP as technical person.

o Senior Software Engineer, Nossa Caixa Bank

Apr 2008 - Dec 2009

- Supported Java, C#, and Cobol developers in different departments.
- Wrote code standards for Java and **.NET** applications.
- Maintained integration code for Java and .NET with Mainframes using Cobol, **MQSeries**, **DirectConnect**, **Uniface**, and Java in Z/OS Linux.
- Developed Java training material, and provided training and interviews to other departments
- Assessment of new tools, providing detailed report to the bank decision makers.

o Junior System Analyst, Claro

Jun 2007 - Mar 2008

- Updated existing MMS adapter, to support new MMS/MM7 protocol in the VAS middleware system, using **Java**, **JEE**, memory buffers, and Java mail API.
- Added **JMS** configuration and code for the new MMS adapter.
- Helped mapping VAS to Billing process, looking for inconsistencies, and working with the revenue assurance team.
- Wrote a **Struts** application to manage broadcast SMS campaings, with scheduling **Quartz** and reporting **iReport**.
- Replaced company web site captcha and added a honeypot.
- Wrote Java code to ETL a complete corporation managed plans (Gestor Online) from Oracle.

o Junior System Technician, Claro

Jan 2006 - May 2007

- Wrote Java code for the JEE middleware platform Swing desktop application

- Troubleshoot **threading** issues in the desktop client.
- Wrote sockets, LDAP clients, and log parsers for the middleware server.
- Maintain the KPI's monitoring panel using applets, and accessed by upper management.

o Value Added Services intern, Claro

Jul 2004 - Dec 2005

- Internship in VAS, with a three month period working with on-going systems, learning how ticket systems work.
- Point of contact for local partners to set up their delivery channels in the VAS middleware system.
- Monitoring the VAS platform logs in HP-UX, Solaris, Linux, and Windows servers.
- Monthly and weekly reports for the VAS, on-going, Web, and upper management.

Technical Training

o Unconscious Bias (3 modules). NIWA / SimTutor. Online.	2020
o Intro to Vue.js, Real World Vue.js, Advanced Components, Next-Level Vue, Mastering	Vuex,
and Vue 3 Composition API . Vue Mastery. Online.	2020
o Building Web Applications in R with Shiny. DataCamp. Online.	2018
o Intermediate R Course - Practice Course. DataCamp. Online.	2018
o Intermediate R Course. DataCamp. Online.	2018
o Introduction to R Course. DataCamp. Online.	2018
o Level 1 Introduction to Sailing Keelboat Certificate. Royal New Zealand Yacht Squ	
Auckland, New Zealand.	2018
 OWASP NZ Day Advanced Web Hacking and Secure Coding. University of Auckland. Auc New Zealand. 	kland, 2017
o AWS Concepts. Linux Academy. Online.	2017
o Apache Spark Essentials. Linux Academy. Online.	2016
o CS107: C++ Programming. Saylor Academy. Online.	2016
o OWASP New Zealand day training. OWASP. Auckland, New Zealand.	2016
o Linux Foundation Certified Systems Engineer. Linux Academy. Online.	2015
o Infrastructure Management with Puppet. Instruct. Sao Paulo, Brazil.	2012
o Basic concepts of change management. Nossa Caixa Bank. Sao Paulo, Brazil.	2008
o CA Harvest Software Change Admin and Config. CA. Sao Paulo, Brazil.	2008
o Hands-On Websphere Application Server. IBM. Sao Paulo, Brazil.	2008
o Business Intelligence. Claro. Sao Paulo, Brazil.	2008
o Information Security. Claro. Sao Paulo, Brazil.	2007
o Biometry applied in computer networks security. Mackenzie University. Sao Paulo, Brazil	. 2007
o Web Development with Servlets and JSP. Sun Microsystems. Sao Paulo, Brazil.	2007
o COBIT and Sarbanes-Oxley. Claro. Sao Paulo, Brazil.	2006
o Genexus Programming. Procwork (Sonda). Sao Paulo, Brazil.	2004
o Microsoft Certified Solutions Associate career. Bras e Figueiredo. Sao Paulo, Brazil.	2003
Certifications	
o Japanese-Language Proficiency Test (JLPT) N4	2019
o gvSIG User Certificate	2018
o Japanese-Language Proficiency Test (JLPT) N5	2018
o LFCE Linux Foundation Certified Engineer	2015
o Professional Scrum Master I (scrum.org)	2011
o ISTQB CTFL Certified Tester	2010
o SCWCD Sun Certified Web Component Developer	2009
o ITIL Foundation V2	2009
o COBIT Foundation V4.1	2009
o CA Software Change Manager Administration	2008
o SCJP Sun Certified Java Programmer	2006
o MCP Microsoft Certified Professional Windows 2000	2003

Interests and Hobbies

- o Bioinformatics, semantic web, linked data, animation pipelines, NLP, fuzzy logic, and GIS.
- o Sci-fi books, short stories, comics, movies.
- o Learning about new cultures, but in special Japanese, Brazilian, and Irish.
- o Slack line, swimming, judo, and soccer.

I wrote articles that have been published in different magazines, and also spoke in conferences in some countries. The complete list is available in my web site. For a list of Open Source projects that I contribute to, look at my GitHub profile. I have three software registered with Brazilian INPI (512018001048-2, 512018001051-2, and 512018001052-0) through Federal University of Amapa Foundation. Mentored in GSoC 2020, a new plug-in for Jenkins called Machine Learning Plug-in. References available upon request.